!
We put two more wheels.
And it's been super-free all week.
Yes, the one that goes by itself is the weak liquid.
That goes together, and then, and now I'm on my
fabric, my stuff is just cool. And the weak liquid takes the fabric,
and you can see how wide the support is. That's better than having one over here.
Okay, let me ask you.
You're quite a light.
You are weak.
Okay, let's start.
Endocrine overview. Endocrine glands.
This lecture is going to be real helpful for Hesse stuff,
because they love to test adrenals and firewalls.
The endocrine overview is only going to be about
thyroid and adrenals. You do not have to know the thymus,
the pineal, the parathyroid.
You don't have to know all those. Just know your thyroid gland.
Know your adrenal gland, and you're good to go.
Now, if you don't know your thyroid, you're in trouble. You don't know your adrenal, you're in trouble.
So focus on what you need to know. So let's focus on those two glands.
The first one is hyperthyroidism that I will talk about in a few minutes.
Hyperthyroidism that I will talk about. Whenever Mark Clemak sees the word thyroidism,
he turns it into metabolism,
because that's what the thyroid does.
The thyroid regulates metabolism.
So when you see hyperthyroidism, what do I want you to turn it into?
Hyper metabolism.
If that is true, do you see that now you do not have to memorize?
The signs and symptoms, they're just logical.
What would be the logical set of signs and symptoms
you would see if you had a high metabolic rate?
Weight loss. So they're skinny and weight loss.
What else?
What would their pulse rate be? Blood pressure.
Blood pressure. Their personality.
Irritable, hyper, obnoxious,
excitable. Life of the party for about five minutes until everybody gets sick of them.
Heat, what?
Intolerance and cold tolerance.
So they can tolerate the cold because they're like a little furnace.
They cannot tolerate the heat because they're already burning up.
Exophthalmos. What's exophthalmos?
Mouldering eyes.
X-E-X.
E-X-O-H-P-O-P-H-T-H-A-L-M-O-S.
Exophthalmos.
So they're basically
they're skinny, they're hyper, they're
tacky, they're hypermetabolic.
The person I remember, this dates me to, you guys probably do not know him,
was a guy named Don Knotts that was
what was he?
Barney Fight on Mayberry.
The skinny little guy, Sheriff Andy Andy,
my guy's skinny, classic hyperthyroid guy.
The name of this disease is Graves.
G-R-A-V-E-S, Graves disease.
Now they will not tell you, they will not say Graves disease, hyperthyroid.
They'll give you one name. And you're supposed to know Graves is hyperthyroid.
The way I remember that is the same my grandma used to say
which is you're going to run yourself into the grave.
What two words does that link?
Run with grave. Well if you're run, run, run, run, run, run all the time, what are you?
Hyperthyroid.
So running yourself into the grave helps me remember it's hyperthyroid.
Number three, the problem here is hyperthyroidism.
So you have three treatment options. You have three ways to treat hyperthyroidism.
Number one, radioactive iodine.
Now there's two things you need to know about radioactive iodine.
Number one, the patient should be
by themselves for 24 hours.
They should be in a room by themselves for 24 hours.
And after that, they have to be real careful
with their urine. They should flush three times.
If they spill their urine on the ground, they need to call the hazmat team.
Because somebody has to come with a Geiger counter
to make sure it's all cleaned up.
So if you have a patient on radioactive iodine for hyperthyroidism
and they spill urine on the floor in the hospital,
you can't call housekeeping.
You gotta call your hospital hazmat team
and they come with all their paraphernalia. It looks really, really silly
for them to go worrying about the urine. But that's where the radioactivity
is excreted is through the urine. So this is the one place
where they have glow in the dark urine. Not really, but you have to treat it
like it's bad. So the only risk to you, the nurse,
for a patient whose had radioactive iodine is what?
Their urine. And give them a private room in the first
24 hours.
Okay, the next treatment we have is PTU.
PTU. A drug. Yes?
When you get family visitation on that, is that an issue I've seen several
ATIs? With radioactive iodine, no family visitation
in the first 24 hours. And if they go home, they are supposed
to stay in the family room and nobody else, or they stay in their bedroom,
nobody else goes in for 24 hours.
So there's a restriction of visitors, home restriction,
for 24. After 24, they can have all the visitors in the world
as long as they don't pee on them.
Okay, the second problem is PTU. Propyl-
thiourosyl. Propyl-
thiourosyl. Now I don't want you to
memorize that PTU is propyl- thiourosyl. What's it used for?
Hypothyroid.
So what must it do
to your thyroid? If it treats hyper, what must it do?
Bring it down. So I want you to remember that
PTU stands for
Puts thyroid under.
Whenever you see
PTU, what should pop in your head? Puts thyroid
under, which tells you it treats hyperthyroid.
Its primary use is for cancer.
It's a cancer drug, but one of its special uses is for hyperthyroid
because you will also put the thyroid under.
So what do you think the number one nursing thing is
with this drug, if it's a cancer drug?
Immunosuppression. So what
blood values do you have to watch when they're on PTU?
Their white blood cell counts.
So it puts the thyroid under and it also knocks
down your white count.
The most common way, however, that we
treat hyperthyroid is surgical removal. We do a thyroid
ectomy. Thyroid ectomy.
We remove part of the thyroid or all of the thyroid.
Now if you want to get
your thyroidectomy questions correct, you must pay attention to
whether they're talking about a total thyroidectomy or
a subtotal thyroidectomy.
Because that's going to make a huge difference in your answer. If you just treat
all thyroid ectomy the same, you will miss loads of questions.
So what's the most important thing in a thyroid question, thyroid ectomy question?
Total or sub? Now I taught this
one time and a student called me the day after and said, what you taught didn't
help. On thyroid ectomy. So I thought, okay. And I said, well what
didn't help? And she said, well there was a different kind of thyroid surgery on
there that you didn't cover. Boy, that's interesting.
Total, subtotal. That pretty much covers it
for me. I can't think of, you know, it's either total or it's
subtotal. I mean, what third possibility could there be?
And I said, well, what was it? And she said, it was a partial thyroid
ectomy.
Subtotal is a partial. Total is a complete.
So a complete thyroidectomy is a total.
A partial is a sub-total. Now if she passed,
you know, so you don't have to be
a real shining light. You just have to do a sub-shining.
She certainly was not a shining light. Why did she make such a dumb mistake?
She wasn't managing her
anxiety. And she was looking for total and subtotal and it wasn't
there. She panicked and she didn't say, now wait a minute.
Which of these is closest to what I do know?
Right? Because it may not say it exactly the way you want it. Remember the guy with
the cracker and the carbohydrate, dry carbohydrate?
You know, they'll say things differently than you learned them, but it means the same thing.
If you see something on the test that says
means the same as something you learned, but it's saying it differently, guess what?
It is what you learned. Don't say, well, that sounds like the
same thing, but I didn't learn it that way, so it's probably not that.
Oh, that is the worst thing to do. You should do the opposite. You should say,
that sounds an awful lot like what I learned, which was this. It's not the same
phrasing, but it sounds like that, so it must be that.
Do you see the difference? Always assume
that if they tell you something synonymous, it means
the same as what you know. Don't assume it's something different.
Always assume it's what you know.
Okay, so for totals, totals need
lifelong hormone replacement. Why?
Because if I take your whole thyroid out, you don't
have any, so you've got to have lifelong hormone replacement. Also,
letter B, you are at risk for hypocalcemia.
Why low calcium?
Why after a total thyroidectomy do you have a low calcium?
Because it's almost impossible to spare the parathyroid
when you take the whole thyroid out, so you end up with low parathormone,
low calcium. So they're at
risk for low calcium. What are the signs and symptoms of hypocalcemia?
We talked about that last hour. Calcium's do the
opposite, so hypocalcemia's going to make
everything go? Up, so you're going to have tetany, spasm, irritability,
clonus, seizure, tachycardia, hypertension, irritability,
jitteriness, tremor.
Right?
What's the first sign that's going to happen?
Parasthesia. Excellent. See, once you start learning enough, things
start cycling around and it's all no news, right? It's old news.
What
two signs will you have?
Tvos, tects, and
two signs. Because your calcium is low.
Okay,
subtotal thyroidectomies on the other hand do not need lifelong
replacement. Why? Because you got some left and it's supposed to kick in.
Might you be on hormone replacement for a little while?
Until that other one kicks in, then it's supposed to be off.
Do you think you get the hypocalcemia much with this?
No, because if you only take out part of it, you can spare your parathyroid
in your calcium spine. However, what these people
are at risk for is something that totals never get, and that is
thyroid storm or thyroid crisis. Same thing.
It also has another name, thyrotoxicosis,
which sounds like a toxic thyroid, so that sounds like hyperthyroidism to me.
Thyroid storm.
Now what are the symptoms of thyroid storm? Four
really bad things. Number one,
super high temperatures of a hundred and five.
Number two,
extremely high blood pressures.
Stroke category. So you're probably talking
210 over 180.
Now I'm just giving you that as a ballpark. That's no
set in stone number.
Severe tachycardia.
Severe tachycardia, probably
in the 180s. Could be as high as 200.
And there again, that's just a ballpark. There's nothing magical about that number.
And lastly,
they are psychotically delirious. They have
psychotic delirium,
which we talked about before.
These people are in a
medical emergency. This thyroid storm
is a very, very bad thing.
Because it can cause brain damage, and brain damage is
permanent. You literally fry your brain to death
with hypoxia. And are hypoxia.
So you must
treat this immediately. And what you treat it with is get the temperature down
and get the oxygen up. Get the temperature down, get the
oxygen up. Well how do you get the temperature down?
What's the first way you would do it?
Ice packs.
What's the best way?
Cooling blanket. Because if you would pack them in ice without the cooling
blanket, use the cooling blanket without the ice, which way
would be better? Ice without the cooling blanket,
cooling blanket without the ice. What's better? Cooling blanket
without the ice. So the best is the cooling blanket. Well what would you do first?
First I'd put them in ice, then I'd order the cooling blanket and have it there.
So you see there's another first best difference.
And what would you, what would you give, how do you get the oxygen up?
Oxygen per mask
at 10 liters.
Just as an interest note, what's the problem with
that order? What do you think you experience when you try to implement
that order?
What's that? And these people are what? Psychonically
delirious. So how likely is it you're going to keep
an oxygen mask on this patient? Yeah, good luck.
Good luck. So this is a medical emergency.
You pack them in ice, order the blanket, throw a mask on them with
high O2. And they will come out of it themselves
without treatment or they will die.
And there's nothing you can do
to make it go either way. It's just when that T3, T4
gets out of their system, they'll be okay. We don't want
to medicate them. Because if we medicate them, it could go the other way.
So this is a self-limiting condition.
All we're doing is sparing their brain until they come out of it.
Now I've seen this about five times in my career.
The longest lasted 12 hours, the shortest lasted
about less than two hours.
But when you're treating these people, it's
two on one. Meaning two staff for
one patient. You need an aide and yourself.
Because you can't do it with just yourself. Yes?
Tylenol works in the hypothalamus
and at this point the hypothalamus is being
severely
threatened. Because it's right near the pituitary and the problem
with the thyroid storm that caused it was the TSH from the pituitary.
So that pituitary hypothalamic access
is part of the problem that's causing this situation.
And Tylenol works in that hypothalamus
and it's not going to work. Tylenol just isn't going to do it.
So you really have to
pack them in ice. So you really don't
treat a lot of it. It's kind of scary because you're just sitting there
doing what you can. Alright. But I would say that good
nursing care is going to save their life. Why? Because medicine isn't.
Yes, question?
Well, I mean, if you had to pick between
the ice packs and the oxygen,
I would do the oxygen first, the ice pack second, the cooling blanket
third. But if I was between the ice packs and the cooling blanket,
the ice packs go first.
But I would always fix stay with my patient.
Because you don't leave your patient to go get the oxygen. Do you know what I'm saying?
But it's a perfect world so it's sitting right there.
Alright. Post-op risks.
They love to ask you about thyroidectomies and post-op risks.
Because it depends on the type of surgery and it depends on the time period.
So let's talk about this. You've got to know this. You have to know this.
In the first 12 hours, it doesn't matter whether it's a total
or a subtotal. It does not matter. The top priority is
airway.
Because where's your thyroid? So if you have a demon in the
area, what's it going to press on?
The airway. The larynx. So trachea. So you've got to watch out.
Second big problem is hemorrhage. Because it's an endocrine gland
which has a lot of blood vessels. So the top two
in the first 12 hours for both types of thyroid
surgery are airway and hemorrhage. Which is pretty much standard,
isn't it? Okay. Now where the difference
comes in is in the 12 to 48 hour window.
If they give you a patient who's longer than 12 hours
but less than 48, now you have to
pay attention to what type of thyroidectomy was done.
Letter A. The post-op risks 12
to 48 hours after a total. The big danger is tetany.
Tetany due to the low calcium.
For a total, they get the tetany because of the low calcium.
However,
letter B, the post-op risks 12 to 48 hours
for a subtotal is storm.
What's storm? Thyroid storm.
So you see where they're different?
But they're the same in the first 12 hours but different in the next 36.
So, 12 to 48 hours
after surgeries, what do totals get?
What do subs get? Totals get
tetany, subs get storm.
Totals get tetany
and subs get storm.
So TTSS. Total tetany, substorm. Total tetany,
subs, total TTSS. When?
12 to 48 hours after surgery. In the first 12, what is it?
Airway and hemorrhain. Hemorrhoea and bleeding for everybody.
What's the big risk
after 48 hours, by the way? Infection.
Right?
How long does it have to be before you're allowed to pick infection as a high priority?
At least 42 hours we'd prefer 72.
Here's the deal. Never pick infection in the first 72 hours
after anything. So if they had a trauma
and it's been 36 hours, would you pick infection? No.
They gave birth to a baby 8 hours ago, would you pick infection? No.
Never pick infection in the first 72 hours. You only pick infection
after 72 hours, not in the first 72.
Question.
Tetany
is dangerous because your larynx can go into a
tetanic laryngeal spasm which would close
the vocal cords in an irreversible spasm which
essentially cuts off your airway and you die.
Okay.
Hypothyroid.
Hypothyroid is hypometabolism.
So hypothyroid is hypometabolism. What are the signs
and symptoms of a low metabolic rate?
If your metabolic rate is really low, what would you look like?
Obese. Or would your personality be?
What's that?
Flat, boring,
dull,
cold, intolerance,
heat, tolerance.
See, you cannot tolerate what you are. So if you're
cold, you have cold intolerance. If you're hot,
you have heat intolerance. Do you see what I'm saying? So hypothyroid
or hypos are always what? Cold.
So they have cold intolerance. Hyperthyroid are always
hot so they have heat intolerance. So you cannot
tolerate what you are. What would the pulse be
and the blood pressure be? Low.
If they were a test taker, what kind of test taker would they be?
Slow. Extremely slow test takers.
They tend to get lower grades in school.
Not because they're not smart, but because they can't process fast enough.
It could even affect nursing practice
in the sense that you don't think fast enough.
Okay, the name of the disease is mixed edema.
M-Y-X, M-Y-X, and then the word
edema. That's the name of it.
Okay, the treatment. Do you have too much hormone or not enough hormone?
Not enough, so what's the logical treatment?
Give them thyroid hormones. Synthroid.
Levothyroxine.
Number four. Caution.
Do not sedate these people. Why do you not sedate them?
Because they're already
super slow. You sedate them, you'll actually put them in a coma.
It's called a mixed edema coma.
So what preop order would you question
with this hypothyroid patient?
Ambien at
H-S, the sleeping pill before surgery.
The night before surgery, because they don't need that.
Let me ask you this. You've got a hypothyroid client. He's on
thyroid pills every day. He's going to have
an open heart surgery. He's scheduled for it in the morning.
Doctor orders NPO past midnight.
You've got a problem with that?
What's your problem? Call it question what?
Okay, because NPO means
nothing and nothing means nothing, including anything.
Which would be a pill. So nothing by mouth
means they're not allowed to have any of their oral pills. Which means you would not give the person
their morning thyroid, which means they would be hypothyroid
and very susceptible to any drug that would sedate them.
Do you get any drugs during surgery that sedate you?
It's called an anesthetic agent. Do you see what I'm saying?
So if you would follow that order and not give the
thyroid pill the morning of surgery, what could likely
happen to your patient? Never make it
off the table. They would die from these
depressant effects of the anesthesia.
So you as a nurse would never hold what
pill before surgery without express
orders to do so. Thyroid pills.
Never hold your thyroid pills
unless they tell you to do it. And even if they told me to do it,
if I called the surgeon and he told me to hold the thyroid, what would I do?
I'd call the anesthesiologist.
And if he said hold it, what would I do?
I'd call
the head of the anesthesiologist, my supervisor
and say hey look, this is not cool.
Now my supervisor should what? Contact the supervisor
of the anesthesiology and say hey look,
what's going on here? You see, you
aren't supposed to go up the ladder outside your department. You go
up your department and they go across.
Do you see what I'm saying? If I really thought it was unsafe,
I would just refuse to follow, I would just refuse to, I don't know.
You understand, if I thought it meant a patient dying, how far would you go?
You know what I'm saying?
If it was your dad, what would you do to keep him from gone surgery?
You'd lay down on the floor and not let him get the card over your
body. Do you know what I mean? So I'm just saying, would you do the same
for your patient? Okay, enough said on that.
Adrenal cortex. The second gland we're going to talk about, the adrenal cortex.
Interestingly, adrenal cortex diseases
start with either the letter A or the letter C
which are the initials of adrenal cortex.
So could graves be
the adrenal cortex? Could myxedema be the adrenal cortex?
Could pheochromocytoma be the adrenal cortex? Could cushings,
cons, adacins, corticoinsufficiency,
adrenal insufficiency? Yes.
So all of those diseases start with an A or a C. Now I didn't say
that all diseases start with an A or a C are adrenal cortex because
asthma, obviously, no.
All right. Addison's disease, let's start with Addison's.
It starts with an A. It's under secretion of the adrenal
cortex, under secretion.
What are the signs and symptoms? Just two things you need to know.
They are hyperpigmented.
What does hyperpigmented mean?
Very tan. Very tan.
So they look what many people call healthy, but they are the farthest
thing from it because the second thing you need to know about it is these people
do not adapt to stress. They do not
adapt to stress
because their adrenal gland is under
secreting. So if they undergo any stress at all,
what could happen?
What's the purpose of the stress response I might ask?
What's the purpose of the stress response?
Not to increase the metabolism necessarily.
Although it will.
That's what mediates it, but that's not the purpose of it.
That's what it does, but that's not what the purpose is.
But what's the big, when you are under stress
there's a threat to your brain.
The purpose of the stress response is to
perfuse the brain with blood, in other words support the blood pressure,
and give the brain glucose, which means raise the blood glucose.
So the purpose of the stress response is to raise the glucose,
raise the blood pressure. Does everybody understand that?
Your stress response is supposed to raise your glucose,
and raise your blood pressure. That's what its
purpose is.
If these people do not have the adrenal
cortex to carry out the stress response,
when they undergo stress, what will happen?
What's the purpose of the
stress response? Raise the, and raise the.
And if you've got a disease in that
organ and cannot do that, what will happen when you undergo stress?
Your glucose will go down
and your blood pressure will go down and you'll go into shock
like that. And it doesn't take much
to put them into shock. In fact
these people have been known to go to the dentist, have a tooth filled,
and they go into full blown shock because of that stress, which wouldn't bother most of us.
If you ever work squad,
these are the people that you happen on the scene of a little fender bender
and somebody's gone. No blood pressure, nothing. They're gone.
And you think, well, they couldn't possibly have been hurt that bad.
Well, what you'll search them and what will you find?
A really nice guy wearing a bracelet.
And what does a bracelet say? I have Addison's
disease. These people, you look at them wrong
and they go into shock. No, not really.
They are your time bombs waiting to go.
This is a very scary disease.
You're okay until something happens
and then wham, they decompose it like that.
It's very rare. As far as endocrine disorders,
it's one of the rarest. It's one of the rarest. It's like for every
600 Cushing's patients I would see,
I see one Addison's. And that's probably being generous.
I probably have only taken care of two or three Addison's patients
in my entire life. Cushing's all the time.
Kennedy was supposed to have had
this disease, JFK. He was rumored to have this disease.
So that means when you got shot, what?
There was no chance. There was no. I mean, even if he hadn't
even if it had been now and it hadn't gotten hit in the skull,
if he had gotten like a shoulder injury now, he might
not have made it. So it was. And think about this.
What's really dangerous to people with Addison's disease?
Stress. You're the president of the United States.
He probably couldn't get elected right now. Because they would have
made such a big deal of the matter. You know what I mean? It would have just disqualified him.
But it was hidden. People didn't know about it.
Well, he was a little bronzer though. Early
years he was and he was real pasty. But then he got tanned as he went on.
And then he started taking steroids so he got puffy.
So the nice little puffy cheeks he had there near the end, that was steroids.
That wasn't Jack.
Well, what's the treatment?
Yeah. Given what he's low on, which is what?
Steroids. Not pulp you all steroids, but
glucocorticoids. All drugs that end in what?
What do all steroids end in?
Zone.
Beta-methasone, Bekla-methasone, dexamethasone,
prednisone, mometasone, hydrocortisone,
so drugs that end in zones are
steroids.
So you give these drugs
to people in adhesins, right? So, adhesins
disease. Is it under secretion or over secretion?
Under secretion. Do you have to take something away
from them or add something to them?
And what do you add?
A zone.
In adhesins you add a zone.
And that tells you whether, doesn't add a zone tell you
whether it's hyper or hypo? Sure. Because if you're adding
it's what? Hypo and it tells you what drugs to pick, anything
ending in zone. So just remember, add a zone, you add a zone.
And that will help you remember it.
Cushings. Cushings syndrome.
This is over secretion of the adrenal
cortex. Over secretion. The way I remember this
is if you have a cushy bank account,
do you have more or less money? More.
If you have a cushy chair, does it have
more or less stuffing? More. If you have a cushy
tushy, do you have
more or less? More. Yeah, you got a whole lot more, right?
So, cushy just sounds like more to me.
Doesn't it? Cushings. Cushy over.
You got to add because it's under. I never forget which one's
under and which one's over. Okay, now, the signs
and symptoms of Cushing's disease, you have to know this. They will
test this and knowing this list gets you what
we call two for the money, which means when you memorize this list
you're actually getting two things. Number one, you're getting the signs and symptoms of Cushing's
and number two, you're getting all the side effects of steroid
medications. So, when you memorize this one list
you're getting two things. Cushing's signs and symptoms and
side effects of steroids. Any drug ending in?
Some. So, that's good for a lot of reasons.
Now, I am going to have you remember this by
drawing a picture of a little man.
And I'm serious, I want you to draw this little guy over and over and
over again until you draw him perfectly. Because if you can
draw him perfectly, guess what? You know the signs and
symptoms of and you know the side effects of
any drug ending in? So, here's what it goes.
Now, this man is called
Cushman.
Now, I'm going to draw a head.
But don't draw the head real big because you need a really big space for a really big body.
So, don't take up all your space with the head.
The first thing on the head is you need to draw
a moon face.
He's got a moon face. And he said, oh, I can't draw. Okay, well,
can you do this?
So, draw a moon face. Whatever your skill set is
just draw a moon face.
Because that's the first symptom, moon face, puffy moon face.
Then,
draw a beard on him.
What's the
fancy term for excess hairiness
on the body? Close.
Close.
Here's suitism.
That means lots of hair.
Okay, next, draw
a real big body. And I mean a big one. Put a bump on the front.
Oh.
And a bump on the back.
Put a bump on the front and a bump on the back.
Now, what's the bump?
Okay, let me ask you this first. What's the, what do we call
the big round body?
Obesity, but a certain type of obesity.
Trunkle or central obesity, they'll call it.
Because see, your arms and legs aren't fat, it's just your body.
Your arms and legs are actually really skinny.
So it's trunkle or central obesity. That's the big body. What's the bump
on the front? No.
The buffalo hump is the bump on the back. Because buffaloes have a bump
on their back. So that's the buffalo hump right there. This is the
gynichomastia.
Co-mastia.
Those are female tight breasts on men.
They sort of wear the bro.
If you remember Seinfeld.
So you have gynichomastia and buffalo hump. As well as
the central obesity. Now,
I want you to draw skinny, skinny arms and
skinny legs. Skinny arms and
skinny legs. Because they have atrophy
of those muscles. Those muscles waste away.
Alright, then I want you to fill him full of what?
What's that? Water.
So he's retaining what? Sodium and water.
He's retaining sodium and water.
So what's he losing? Out the back. What's he losing?
Potassium.
He's losing potassium.
Okay, put some
striae on him. What are striae?
S-T-R-I-A-E. Stretch marks.
He has these stretch marks on his abdomen. Striae.
Then,
the most important one of all to remember.
This is the most important one. Put high
glucose if you have room. High glucose.
Because this causes them to be hyperglycemic.
They look like diabetics.
So if you're on a steroid,
and you're diabetic, talk to me.
Diabetic, put on a steroid.
What's that? You need more insulin
because the steroid is going to increase the blood's glucose
and you're going to go out of control.
What's that?
Now I want you to put bruises
all over him. Because what does he do real easily?
He bruises extremely easily.
We're almost done. We only have two things left.
The last thing is I want you to make him say something.
You know how they have those little cartoons, speech balloons?
Have him say something and what he says is,
I'm mad.
I have an infection.
Well that tells you two things about him. What's the first thing it tells you?
He's grouchy. He's irritable.
Secondly, he's immunosuppressed.
So if you asked me, Mark, what are the signs and symptoms of Cushing's syndrome?
Or what are the side effects of steroid meds? I would close my eyes.
Why? I'd be picturing him and I'd say,
okay, moon face, here's the tism.
Central obesity, got to come out of the bubble, retaining water,
losing potassium, high glucose, wasting extremities,
striae, bruising, irritability,
and immunosuppression. And who did I describe?
I have this vision and I went down through
and I went through and I went through.
One of the famous ways that people ask it is they'll give a person with an acute
observation of COPD in which they need
a steroid IV push every eight hours to reduce the inflammation
in the airways. And it's a steroid.
And they'll ask what nursing action needs to be taken when they're on this steroid?
Accu-checks, Q6.
Because what do steroids make your sugar do?
Go up, even if you're not diabetic. And if you are diabetic, look at it.
Okay, so you got push man?
I'm serious about drawing him because if you don't draw him and don't learn him,
many of you in here are going to say, oh nuts when you get onto your
tests because you're going to wish you had.
Now what's the treatment? Well the question is, do you have too much or too little here?
Too much. What's the classic treatment for
hyper secretion of a gland?
What's the number one treatment for a hypersecretory gland?
Cut it out. So adrenal ectomy.
Well what happens if you do a bilateral adrenal ectomy, do you think?
If you do a bilateral adrenal ectomy.
What does that mean? Do you have any adrenals left?
So what do you have? Addison.
Okay, now think about it. Why did you do
a bilateral adrenal ectomy? What did you look like
that made the doctor do a bilateral adrenal ectomy?
Looked like a push man, right? So he did that to prevent that.
But once you do that, you can induce what disease?
Addison, for which you give a
steroid ending in so.
The side effects of which now make you look like
a push man, which is why you had the surgery. So it's really
frustrating. I mean it is, it's like, it takes like a year
or two to get them equilibrated back to where they're getting
feeling normal. And that's the problem with endocrine
surgery. The endocrine surgery creates the opposite
problem for which you have to take the hormone, the
side effects of which make you look like the thing you had in the first place.
So think about if you're hyper
thyroid, high thyroid, thyroid now, what's the
major treatment? Thyroidectomy.
And if you do a total thyroidectomy, what do you induce?
Hypothyroid, for which you have to take
thyroid pills. What are the side effects
of thyroid pills? They look like
Graves' disease, which is the reason you had the surgery in the first place.
You see, any endocrine gland works that way. It's really frustrating
to these poor people. And it takes years to get it back to normal.
Okay, let's finish up.
For today we have probably two things to do
and will be done.
Let's talk about toys on page 33. Kids' toys.
Children's toys.
This is a lecture about
selecting the appropriate play activity or toy
given the age of the child, generally speaking. Now
when you select toys or play activities for children
there are usually three things to consider.
I'm just going to walk you through the graph and keep talking. Three things to consider. The first one, is it
safe?
The second one, is it age appropriate?
The third one, is it
feasible?
You have to make sure that the toys you're using are safe,
age appropriate, and feasible.
Sorry, my back's killing me. I can't stand it anymore.
First thing, safety.
Safety considerations when you're thinking of toys.
There are three things you have to consider with safety of a toy. The first
thing is, number one, no small toys
for children under four.
If you've got a four year old kid or younger, you should not pick a toy that has
small parts they could aspirate. If they're over four,
guess what? The small parts are just
fine. So four is your cut off age for small
pieces parts to toys. Second thing you
consider for safety. Number two, no
metal, M-E-T-A-L, no metal
toys. If oxygen is in use,
if they're getting oxygen,
why? Sparks.
Does anybody know a fancy word they might use in place of metal?
That means the same thing as metal?
Diecast.
D-I-E-C-A-S-T, diecast.
If they say a diecast car, they're talking about one of those
metal matchbox things. And that's a no-no if oxygen
is in use. Third safety consideration. Number three
safety consideration. And this is more vocabulary than anything.
Write down beware
of fomites.
F-O-M-I-T-E-S. Beware of fomites.
Now you guys should be asking me what in the world is a fomite?
A fomite is a non-living
object that harbors microorganisms.
It has to be non-living and it harbors
microorganisms. By the way,
just to see if you know your epidemiology,
what do you call a living organism
that harbors microorganisms? A vector
or a host. But this is a non-living
so it is a fomite.
Now why in the world are we talking about
fomites with kids?
Toys are notorious fomites
in a pediatric war. They stick them in their mouth
the next kid sticks it in their mouth.
I mean, it's just really bad. So toys
are horrible. Now which toys make
worse fomites than other toys?
What toys are the worst fomites? Stuffed animals.
What makes the best toy because it's unlikely to be a fomite?
Hard plastic. What can you do with hard plastic toys that you cannot
do with stuffed animals?
Bleach them until they're dead. You know what I mean? You can terminally disinfect
a hard plastic action figure.
You can't
terminally disinfect tickle-me-el-on.
So if you have a child that is immunosuppressed
what would be the best
toy for that child?
A hard plastic action figure.
Alright, those are the safety considerations.
Feasibility just means could you do it?
In a pretty common sense. For example,
can a 13 year old is swimming a good activity for a 13 year old?
Is it safe for a 13 year old?
Is it age appropriate for a 13 year old? Is it feasible
for a 13 year old in a body cast? No. See, so
feasibility can come into this too, but that's just going to be common sense.
In other words, feasibility means could you actually play it
with this child in this situation they're in?
The next one is age
appropriate. This will take up the majority of the lecture because this is what they test
for. They want to know if they give you a kid of a certain age what
toy should you give them. So let's start out with the first year of
life, infancy. From zero to six months of age
the best toy is a musical mobile.
The best toy is a musical mobile.
Because these kids are sensory motors.
They are sensory motors. So the best toy is something that
stimulates both motor and sensory. That's why the musical
mobile is best. However, if the boards does not have musical mobile
there, your second best answer is to look for something
hard, meaning what?
You know, something that can be distant. No, did I say hard?
It needs to be soft right now.
But it has to be large.
Why large? So they don't choke. Why soft?
So they don't hurt themselves.
What's the problem? Well, the problem is what do you do with a three-month
old who is supposed to have soft toys
if that three-month old is also immunosuppressed?
You see the treatment problem there? Boards won't go there.
Because that's a conflict of two principles.
If you're just happy, you know the principles, period. So don't go there.
But you do see the inherent problem in that, don't you?
Now, let's talk about the six- to
nine-month-olds. These kids are working
on a skill called object permanence.
Have you heard of object permanence? What does that mean?
Yeah, the idea
that it's still there even if you cannot see it. For example, if a child does not
have object permanence,
if I put their favorite toy under a blanket, what will they do?
Crap.
Because it's what? Gone. Into that
third dimension, that eighth dimension. Never to be seen again.
If a child has object permanence,
and you put their favorite toy
under a blanket, what will they do? Rip off the blanket
and grab the toy. You see, it's very different.
Now, at six to nine months of age, your
play should be teaching them that.
That is the big task they need to learn intellectually.
So you should play with them with toys and activities
that teach them object permanence. So the best toy
is what I call a cover-uncover toy.
Cover-uncover toy.
Now, I cannot tell you exactly what
toy they will use.
But I can tell you what kind of
toy you should select. So you should select
for a six to niner, you should select a toy where you cover it up
and then you uncover it. Then you cover it up
and then you uncover it. What is that teaching them?
Object permanence. So could you give me some examples
of cover-uncover toys? Jack-of-the-box.
Those pop-up
pals, remember?
You push the right button, they pop up, then you push them down, then you pop up, then they push them down.
Those books that have the little windows
and then, you know, where are the birdies? Oh, there they are.
Where are the birdies? Oh, there they are. Where's the birdies? There they are.
And you're cover-uncover in the little picture. The birdies in the nest.
That's perfect for this station. Fantastic.
Playing Peek-a-boo.
Why?
You're there, then you're not. You're there, then you're not. That's good.
Putting a blanket over your head and then uncovering your head.
That's really cool. That's good. And then what you do is they start laughing
and then you stop doing it and see if they're learning
because if they're learning, they'll pull the blanket off and laugh because they don't.
They'll go...
Actually, do you guys know a question about dogs?
That's how you test a dog's intelligence.
Because one of the highest order cognitive skills a dog can
perform is cover is object permanence.
And if you throw a blanket over your dog and it just sits there like this,
you got a dumb dog.
If you throw the blanket over the dog and he goes, oh, yeah, then you got a good dog.
Yes, smart dog. So you'll know how dumb your dog is tonight.
Some of you say,
I do that to my husband and he doesn't take off that hat.
Well, what's the second best toy if a cover,
uncovered toy does not show up? Something
large but it should be hard.
So you can make it a plastic wood
metal. So how old does a child need to be
before they're allowed to play with anything made of wood, metal, and hard plastic?
At least six months of age.
By the way, what is the worst toy
in the world for a six to nine month old kid?
The absolute worst toy.
The musical mobile.
What was the best toy for a kid before six
months? The musical mobile. What's the worst toy
for a kid after six months? The musical mobile. Why?
Because now they pull themselves up, they sit up, and they
strangulate. Many, many kids
strangulations or near strangulations from the musical mobiles.
They should have been taken out of the nursery months ago.
The next age group are
the nine to twelve monthers, right? And these kids are working on
vocalization. They're learning to speak.
So what kind of toys are best for these kids?
Speaking toys, talking toys,
verbal toys. Now I'm not going to give you a specific one
because I don't know what they're going to test. But this is going to be like
Woody the cowboy, Teddy Ruxpin,
Tickle Me Elmo, Slap Me Susie.
I don't know all of them.
All those ones where you gotta watch. You gotta string
and you pull the string and it says something that's really cool.
See and say
barnyard friends, you know, the cow says, move. Fantastic
for this age group. Talking boys. What kind of books?
Talking books.
Really good for this age group.
If we just talked about books alone, what's a good book for a kid under six
months? Stop booking and go what?
Ha! What's a good book for a
kid six to nine or?
Picked window books. What's the best
book for a nine to twelveer? Speaking books.
Talking books.
The other thing about a six to nineer that's down here is purposeful
activity with objects. Purposeful activity.
In other words, how old does a child have to be
before they'll do anything purposeful with a toy?
At least nine months.
So let me ask you this. Could a seven month old play
with three wooden blocks?
Could they play with three wooden blocks? Is wood okay?
Because they're over six months. They could play with three wooden blocks.
Could a seven month old build a tower
of three wooden blocks? Why? Why not?
Build is a purpose word
and you cannot pick any answers that have
purpose words in them until the child is at least how old?
Nine months. So here's the deal. Never pick
answers with the following words in it if the kid is
under nine months. Never pick an answer
with the following words in it if the
kid is under nine months.
So here are those words. Build.
Sort. Stack.
Make.
Construct.
Why?
Those are purpose words and a kid does nothing purposeful
before age nine months.
I tell people a baby's in the womb how long?
Nine months. And it's another nine months after they're out so they do anything
purposeful. Prior to that it's all random.
Okay. Let's talk about the toddlers.
Which are the one to three year olds.
They are the best toy for them
is a push pull toy.
Something that you push something that you pull.
Now I don't know what it's going to be but give me some examples of push pull toys.
The lawn mower, the wagon, the buggy,
that stupid pauper and paupery thing. What else?
Shroller. Yeah baby strollers. The little dog with the floppy
feet that you drag behind you.
So anything that they push, anything that they pull, fantastic
for one to three year olds. Work on the gross
motor skills. Work on gross motor which is running,
jumping.
I always say if it takes finger
dexterity, no for the toddler.
If you're sitting there thinking now which of these activities could a toddler do?
If any of those activities take finger dexterity
do not choose it for the toddler.
Toddlers do not have finger dexterity. So could they use colored
pencils? No. Scissors? No.
Not even blunt scissors they can't use.
So anything that requires finger dexterity is no
for the toddler. The interesting thing is
people have misnamed finger painting.
Finger painting is not
finger painting. Finger painting is
hand painting. Can toddlers
do finger painting? Yes because it takes your hand
not your diversity of the toddler.
With their fingers?
No they don't. So it's
hand painting not finger painting.
Can they do anything that takes finger dexterity? No.
But they can't do finger painting because finger painting isn't
finger painting, it's hand painting. That's where people get confused. Does that make sense?
They're characterized by
parallel play. Parallel. Which means you play alongside
but not with.
You play alongside but not with.
Okay let's talk about
preschoolers the next stage group. So preschoolers
work
on their fine motor.
So what do you pull at now?
Take your finger dexterity.
Preschool is the finger dexterity.
Number two work on their balance.
So tricycles,
tumbling class, dance class,
ice skates, those are okay at this stage.
Don't put your toddler in dance class, gymnastics class, and walking class.
Not going to work.
When they turn preschool they'll learn in two weeks everything they
would have learned in two years is a top. So it's a waste of your money.
Yes?
Swimming is different because that's more gross motor
in some sense it doesn't really depend on balance. So infants
should actually be taken for swim lessons because of safety issues.
So an infant should be taught how to swim. At least know how to
be used to being in the water.
I would say probably, I don't know what age, anybody know
the age where swimming is?
Zero to three? I was going to say
as soon as you can walk.
But I don't think there's any lower
limit. Like you said zeros, but I know.
What else?
They are characterised,
work on balance,
they're characterised by co-operative play.
Co-operative play, which means what?
As opposed to parallel.
Parallel plays alongside but not
with co-operative plays, so they play with
each other in groups, they interact and play together.
And lastly they like to
pretend they are highly imaginative.
That their pretend plays big.
You know, you be the sheriff,
I'll be the saloon keeper, you be the barmaid, I'll be the outlaw,
you know, you all role play.
I grew up in Youngstown,
I always got to be the bowler.
I was the one with the wagon,
so I was, I got to be the bowler.
Okay, I know you care. Okay, the next thing to do is the school age.
And the school age kids
are characterised by the three C's. They are
created, in other words, let them make it, don't you make it
and give it to them. In other words, would it be
good to give them a colouring book and crayons?
What would be better? Light paper and colored pencils.
Because then they can create their own pictures rather than
fill in the blanks, you know. Would you give them plastic cookies,
plastic lemonade and plastic donuts and have them have a tea party?
No, could they have a tea party? Yes, but what would a school
age, what would you do with a school age? They make the what?
Cookies, they make the lemonade, they make the muffins
and they have a, you see what I'm saying? That's why
Legos is such a good age, toy for this age, because why?
They're building and making, they're creating.
You don't give them trucks and cars, you give them things that they make into
cars and trucks and that kind of thing. That's why Transformers is good because it
makes the creativity and all. Okay, second C
they are collective, they're always collecting something.
Beanie Babies, Pogs, Digimon, Pokemon,
Webkin, what was the stupid one that was Christmas?
Zuzu Pets. Zuzu Pets. You know,
all that kind of stuff. And don't the toy manufacturers
know this? Oh yeah. Remember about five years ago,
because I had girls, so five years, six years ago, Mattel
came out with Barbie and the not two,
not four, not six, not eight, not ten,
but twelve dancing princesses.
Because they knew that all the little girls would want what? All twelve. So why
would you give Barbie and the two dancing princesses? That's stupid.
What a bad marketing plan. You know, go twelve. You know, they'll buy them.
So, you know, that's toys. They know all that stuff.
And lastly, they are competitive.
Which means
they like to play games where there's a winner and a loser. Now, they
don't like being the loser. I never said that. But I'm saying
that if you go over here to the fifth grade, it's in the Earth Elementary
School, and you tell them, we're going to play a game, what do they say? Yeah.
Cool. Get out of school. Play a game. Cool. But if I tell them it's fifth
graders, guess what? Everybody's
going to win. Nobody's going to lose.
We're all going to get the same prize. What will they say?
Stupid game.
Give you this dumb prize and don't waste my time.
But if I tell them, hey, we're going to play a game. Four hundred dollars in a
bike for the kid that wins.
Oh my goodness. I'll have those kids doing all
of them. Tim and Gals, you know. They'll be doing
everything. So,
they like competition. Now, what about preschool?
Make a statement about competition and preschool.
No, not unless you want a room full of screaming, crying kids.
Who wins in preschool? And what do they get?
The same prize. And I'm talking to the same
prize. Don't go in with orange lollipops
and grape lollipops. Go in with
one size, one flavor. And if
they don't like it, they don't get it. Don't go in with two.
You're going to have a Chernobyl.
Forget about it. Adolescence.
What's their play? Peer group association.
Peer group association. They want to what?
Hang out with their friends. Hang out with their friends.
So, do they do
much? Sleep? Have you ever seen a group of teenagers
I have girls so I'm suspicious as a father
so I'd build a rec room on our house so that the pool table and the TV
and everything would be in whose house? Our. So that all the people would come to
our house so I could keep a little... I didn't tell about
the closed circuit television. You know, I don't know.
But they would all come over to our house. You know, 20 of them.
And guess what they do?
20 of them.
So I'd go in the room and I'd say,
how about if we play bowl? Dad?
How about if we watch the word dad? Except for four hours.
You know, and I'd go in and here's my daughter.
Text him.
And I'd say, Emily, who are you texting? Bethany? Bethany who? Bethany
whales. Emily, Bethany's sitting right over there. Yeah, I know.
We're texting each other in the same room. We've got all these boring
teenagers doing nothing. I know. I know. I won't forget it.
They just hang out. Now, what's that got to do with nursing? Here's the deal.
If they gave you a question where a gang of teenagers, five, six, seven, eight
of them, were hanging out in one teenager's room, what do you do?
Do you let them or not let them?
You let them. Unless one of three conditions is happening. Here are the three
things that would... Well, no, not what you're thinking.
Unless one of these three things is true, you let them hang out.
The first thing is if anyone is fresh
out, they should be close down. In other words, if anyone of those
teenagers, adolescents, is less than 12 hours
out of surgery, they shouldn't be hanging out.
Second thing, if anyone is immunosuppressed,
they shouldn't be, for obvious reasons, correct?
And thirdly, if anyone has a contagious disease.
So if you've got 13 kids hanging out
in one room, unless somebody is fresh out, somebody is contagious, or somebody is immunosuppressed,
let them hang out. Get over your control
issues. Let them hang out.
Let's do the last lecture of the day, Lamb Anectomy.
Lamb Anectomy.
What page? 38. I'm not going to do Lamb
Values at this time of day. Your brain will go totally dry.
Lamb Anectomy.
Lambana are the vertebral spinous processes, and
ectomy means removal.
So Lamb Anectomy. Ectomy means removal.
And the Lambana are the vertebral spinous
processes. Vertebral
spinous processes. Now,
what are the vertebral spinous processes? Well, let me ask you this. Have you ever felt
the bumpy bones on the back of somebody?
You're not really feeling the body of the vertebrae. You're feeling
those wingy thingies out the back. Those are the Lambana.
So in a Lamb Anectomy, do I remove
the round bodies of the vertebrae?
No, you'd be an invertebrate if I did. That wouldn't be good.
What I'm removing is those winged things out the back. I removed those.
So we're just removing the posterior
processes of the vertebral bones.
Just part of them. Now, the question is why in the world
did you do that? What's the reason for a Lamb Anectomy?
The reason is to relieve nerve root compression.
Because sometimes when the nerve roots come out of the spinal cord,
there's like calcium or herniated discs
or inflammatory masses pressing on them.
And that causes problems. So we cut away that bone
to give the nerve more room to exit.
So it relieves the compression on the nerve root.
Well then, what are the signs and the symptoms of the
nerve root compression? The three P's. Pain,
parasthesia,
which means what? Numbness and tingling.
And parecis, which is
muscle weakness.
Pain, parasthesia, and parecis. Those are the three signs that your
nerve roots are being pressed upon.
For which we would do a Lamb Anectomy to remove
those back bony parts so that your nerve roots can come out
real nicely and not be pressed on.
Now, when you get a Lamb Anectomy
question, the most important thing to pay attention to
is the most important thing that you pay attention to
in any neuro question. Does anyone know what
the most important thing to pay attention to in any neuro question is?
Location. It is location.
If you want to get a neuro question correct,
pay attention to the location of the problem.
Because the location will determine the symptoms.
The location will determine the prognosis.
The location will determine the treatment.
Location is everything in neuro.
There are three locations for Lamb Anectomies.
They are cervical, thoracic, and lumbar.
Cervical, thoracic,
and lumbar. Cervical means the neck,
thoracic means the upper back, and lumbar means the lower back.
Now, I and the rest of this
page, on the rest of this page, I'm going to illustrate for you
how when you change the location, you change
the answer to the question. So let's talk about it.
Is the next one F or E? E.
Letter E. What is the most important pre-op assessment
for a cervical Lamb Anectomy?
What's the most important word in that question? Cervical. Cervical.
Okay, so the cervical spinal cord intervates two things.
Diaphragm and arms. Diaphragm
and arms. That's what your cervical intervates.
So, if you are doing a pre-op assessment
for a patient going for a cervical Lamb Anectomy, what is the most
important thing you would check out before surgery?
What? Breathing. Why?
Cervical intervates the diaphragm.
So breathing is number one. Check out their breathing.
How are they breathing? Number two, if that is
not there, breathing isn't there, the next best answer is
the function of their arms and hands. That would be your
backup answer. So what's number one answer for cervical?
Breathing. What's number two answer for cervical?
Arms and hand function.
However, letter F,
what did I change in the question?
Location. I changed it from cervical to
thoracic and when I changed location I changed the answer.
It is no longer breathing and arms and hands.
For thoracic, the most important assessment is the cough
and the bowels. Cough
mechanism and bowels.
Cough and bowels. So what would
be the most important thing to assess before thoracic surgery?
How well the patient coughs. Not so much
get, but how they cough. So what I want you to do is this, I want to illustrate
how this is. Your thoracic spinal cord
activates your abdominal muscles and your gut muscles.
So what I want to do is give
I want you to do this. I want you to put your hand on your abdomen
on your abdominal muscles. I want you to cover your mouth
and I want you on my signal I want you to cough. And when you cough I want
you to feel what happens here underneath your hand. Okay, ready?
Cough. How many felt a contraction? Great.
Okay, now I'm going to give all of you a thoracic
spinal cord injury.
Okay?
So now you can no longer contract what?
Your abdominal muscles. So relax them. Relax them. You're paralyzed. There.
You cannot contract those muscles. You're paralyzed. Okay, now put your hand on
your abdomen. They're paralyzed. Cover your mouth.
And this time on my signal I want you to cough. But don't you
dare contract these muscles because you're not allowed to because you're paralyzed
there. Okay, ready? Cough. Well, some of you actually
got a good cough now. Usually that's impossible.
So in order to cough
what do you have to be able to do? Contract these muscles. And if you can't contract these muscles
you cannot cough. You can't. But you can't cough.
How can you breathe? You can breathe but you cannot
cough. So what assessments
do you have to make for a thoracic? Coughing and bowel sounds.
Right? But what about G? What did I
change in G? The location. When I changed the location
I changed the answer. The lumbar
innervates the bladder and the legs. Bladder and legs.
So what's the most important assessment
before lumbar laminectomy?
Yeah, when was the last time they avoided? Is their bladder distended?
Or is it empty? You need to know that before
surgery. And then if that's not there what's the backup answer?
Function of arms and legs.
So that's important. Knowing that.
So cervical is what? Cervical is?
Breathing and arms.
Thoracic is? Coughing and
bowel. Lumbar is?
Bladder and legs.
Let's turn the page and talk about post-op laminectomy.
The number one post-op answer on
the page for laminectomy is log roll.
If you have a question that says log roll your patient
and it has anything to do with spinal cord, including laminectomy,
what's your top answer? Log roll.
You always pick log roll if it's there. You cannot go wrong
by picking log roll.
Now in addition to knowing that there are three other things you need to know about
clients after spinal surgery. Number one, do not dangle
these people. Do not dangle them. Now dangle
does not mean to hold them by their ankles out the window.
What does dangle mean? Sit on the edge of the bed.
Which is what we do for everybody. Isn't that the first thing we do for all post-ops?
Dangle them? What am I telling you about these people? Don't do that.
Go from lying down immediately to what?
Walking around. None of this dangle business.
Now can they sit on the edge of the bed long enough to overcome
orthostatic hypotension? Sure, but they shouldn't
sit there for 10, 15 minutes dangled. Yes?
So fully specified as like feet flat on ground sitting on edge of bed?
Sitting on edge of the bed with feet flat on ground is not
appropriate for a fresh post-op laminectomy.
They say sitting at the side of the bed long enough to overcome
orthostatic hypotension then it's okay for a laminectomy. But if they say
sitting with the feet on the ground, sitting with the feet not on the ground, dangling
none of that for a laminectomy. Sitting is a horrible position for a laminectomy.
Okay, number two restriction. Do not
sit for longer than 30 minutes. They're not allowed to sit
for longer than 30 minutes.
So what kind of typical post-op order would you
question with a laminectomy? What typical post-op
order would you question with a laminectomy?
Up in chair.
For one hour TID. Isn't that real common? Up in chair
for two hours TID. Real common. Up in chair for meals is
really not bad. So how long does a meal usually last? About
a half hour. So that's not bad.
Because they would say up in chair for meals is good because you're only up for a half hour.
So they'd say that's okay.
Third thing. They may walk, stand, and lie down
without restrictions. They may walk,
stand, and lie down without restriction.
So there's only a restriction on what position?
Sitting.
All the OSHA studies since 1970s
have proven what is the one hospital
worker
position, the designation that has the highest
incidence of back injuries. What
worker in the hospital has the highest risk
of back injuries? Not nurses.
Not nurse aides. Admitting clerks.
Because what do they do all day? Sit.
And that's worse than lifting and slugging 200
counters in the bed. It's worse for you. It's terrible.
So sitting is more of a position for your back.
Okay. Let's talk about post-op complications.
What will the post-op complications depend on?
Location. So what would be the number one post-op complication after a
cervical laminectomy? Breathing is not a complication.
It's a good thing.
They won't breathe very well
and very deeply after surgery. They will have trouble breathing
deeply after surgery. What will develop?
Pneumonia. Yes, pneumonia is the number one complication. Why?
Because they don't breathe so well. Why? Because it's a cervical.
And cervical don't breathe so well after the surgery.
Because that's the location that hits the lungs.
Okay. Well, what if they change it to a thoracic?
The post-op complication after thoracic. What would it be?
What won't they do so well?
So what will they get then? Pneumonia. Pneumonia. And they'll have
an ilius because their valves won't work.
But what's the number one problem after a lumbar laminectomy?
Urinary retention.
Followed by problems with the legs.
Do you see where they can
trick you and they can say, a person underwent
a lumbar laminectomy ten hours ago.
What's the number one problem? A, airway, B, breathing,
C, circulation, D, urinary retention.
What would be the answer? Urinary retention. Because they don't have A
and B and C problems because it doesn't affect them.
You see? So that's not what they would do.
Let me ask you this.
You are caring for a patient with a lumbar
oligodendrogliocytoma.
What is the number one problem?
A,
airway, B,
ilius, C, cardiac
arrhythmia, D,
urinary retention.
What would be the answer?
D. Because it's a what? Lumbar.
And it doesn't matter if it's a lumbar.
And it doesn't matter what it is. You don't have to even know what this is.
This does not determine your answer.
What determines your answer? Location does.
So all you have to do is if you know that
cervical is breathing and arms, thoracic is
cough and bowels and lumbar is bladder
and legs, you got the whole thing.
Because all you have to do is look at the location because the pathology doesn't matter.
Could I put a lumbar abscess?
And wouldn't it be the same thing? Lumbar surgery,
same thing. Lumbar spinal cord injury, same thing.
Lumbar appendomoma, same thing.
So what determines pathology in neuro?
Location. Which makes it actually easier.
Okay.
Typically we don't have chest tubes with laminectomies,
but the anterior thoracic will have chest tubes.
Let her see. Let her see the anterior thoracic will have chest tubes.
What does anterior thoracic mean?
Anterior. From the front through the
thoracic you go to the spine.
From the front to the spine through the front of the thorax you're going to
have a pneumohemothorax and knee chest tubes.
Right? Okay. Number five.
Laminectomy with fusion. And the key word here is with fusion.
That means they take a bone graft
from the iliac crest.
So laminectomy with fusion involves
taking a bone graft from the iliac crest. Here's what they do with this one.
Here's your vertebrae.
Here's your vertebrae. Here's your disc.
If they take the disc out, you cannot have bone
on bone. So they have to take some bone
from your hip, bring it over here, put it in between
these and fuse it.
So that you don't have that grinding. So this is a laminectomy
with fusion. Not all laminectomies
have fusion. Most laminectomies don't. In most laminectomies
all you're taking off is this wing thing out the back
and you're not messing with the disc. But if you remove
the disc, then you've got to do a fusion. And you've got to
get bone from somewhere and one place we get it is from the patient's
own hip. So if you have a
laminectomy with fusion, how many incisions will the
patient have? Two. One where? Hip
and one on the spine. So turn the page.
Of those two incisions, which one will have the most
pain? The hip will.
Believe me. That hurts.
Which one has the most bleeding and drainage?
The hip. That's where the hemovac will be. That's where the JP
will be. Which one has the highest risk for
infection? Actually they're equal. They have a 50-50 chance of
infection. And which one has the highest risk for rejection? The spine.
So if you look at the two incisions
postoperatively, which one causes the most problems?
The hip does. So
surgeons are wanting to get rid of that hip incision.
Why do the surgeons want to get rid of that hip incision?
Because it's shorter recovery, a lot better, no problems.
Cuts the infection rate in half, decreases the drainage by 80%,
decreases the pain by 80%. A lot better all the way around.
Hospitals love it because they get money for shorter stay. They make more
profit. That's why here it says
surgeons are using cadaver bone from bone banks.
Why?
Yeah, because if they're going to cut this disc out, they can take
bone from a dead person, put it in between your bones, and
fuse it, and there's not that second incision. So they use that
quite a bit. There is a slight
increased risk of rejection, but not that bad because bone
is not protein, and protein is what triggers the antigen
antibody response, the immune response.
Nowadays, they're even moving away from cadaver bone to guess what?
Synthetic bonding
substances that we are developing in the lab.
But that's not on boards yet.
Okay, discharge teaching. Is this important?
Oh yeah. Discharge teaching, very, very important.
There are four permanent, I mean four temporary restrictions
and three permanent ones after laminectomies.
The first temporary, do not sit for longer
than 30 minutes.
How long do you think that restriction applies?
How many weeks? Six weeks.
If you have to guess how long
something should be restricted and you do not know, you should always
pick six weeks because that will pay off for you.
If you know how long to restrict it, then pick that, but if you don't
pick six weeks, you'll be surprised at how well that pays off.
Number two, lie flat and log rule
for six weeks. Now that doesn't mean
you have to actually do it for six weeks continuously. That just means when you do
turn, log rule and do life flat for that six week period of time.
Number two, no driving for six weeks.
And do not lift more than five pounds for
six weeks. And how heavy is it? What
common household object is about five pounds?
I know
a lady that had back surgery, laminectomy,
when her infant was like nine months old.
And that was disaster. Why?
She couldn't pick them up and what does a nine month old always want?
That kid learned to walk real fast. I mean that kid was walking
ten months. Like whoa, well you know necessity is the mother
of invention, you know. So that kid really learned.
Permanent restrictions.
Laminectomy patients will never be allowed to lift objects by bending
at the waist. How should they lift objects?
Lift with the knees.
Well everybody should be that way.
Right? Should anybody do this? You should all do it with your knees.
That way you get bilateral knee replacements instead of a laminectomy.
Second thing,
cervical lambs, cervical lambs are not allowed
to lift anything over their head.
Nothing goes over your head
with a cervical lamb for the rest of your life.
So can a cervical lamb do this?
This? Yes. That?
No, not even with a feather. So they need step stools in their house.
And then no off trail biking,
jerky amusement park rides, or horseback riding for obvious
reasons. You know the percussion stuff.
So that's laminectomy. But understand,
this lecture on laminectomy can be used
to get any spinal cord questions
correct. Correct? Maybe it's not true? Because you're going to pay attention to what?
Location. And that's where it's going to pay off.
Okay, so Mark, for the last
day, and I think,
let me see, we covered one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, six.
We did eighteen already, and we have one, two,
eight to go, right? Is it eight to go?
And we did probably ten today.
So we have less to do tomorrow than we did today.
So we'll see you tomorrow.
And we've not even been together for more than 24 hours.
This is amazing.
Anyway,
I know,
I know, I know.
That's why, this is what the books, you have to go with what the books
says, and this is the books that we use.
There is usually
gilliest time here, because I'm talking
about the classic.
The classic is always about hopping and bouncing.
What's this?
Popping and now?
Yes, and that's number two.
Sort of built on it, but not built on it.
This re-war pillar was called the mobility,
because Erickson is psycho-social development.
Toys are a lot more popular than you.
You play a game of choice,
then you're psychologizing.
Yes, that book is
that book that someone says, well I can't stress it enough, but that
is only the stuff that you can do. I can't learn it for you.
You just have to put it all the time somewhere.
I know a lot of people just don't do that, but that's the way it all works.
If you put in the time, it'll pay off.
And the moment you're popping and bouncing,
urinary and leg problems,
and pneumonia,
show for watching pneumonia.
Oh, but anyway, we can always re-check.